[Music]
hi everyone this is a video tutorial
about aromatic compounds so we're
basically going to look at the three
characteristics that make a compound
aromatic and how you can apply that to
an example to determine whether or not a
specific compound does fall in the
aromatic bracket so if we take a look
here you'll see that we have three basic
rules for an aromatic compound the first
one is it has to be cyclic so it could
be a three-membered ring or a
six-membered ring but as long as it is a
closed Cy
the second thing is it has to be planer
so any and all atoms involved in that
cyclic component of your structure even
if it's a bigger structure have to be
SP2 hybridized the third and final piece
is that you're going to have to have an
odd number of P Cloud electron pairs so
let's see what this looks like in
practice okay so now let's
systematically apply these three rules
to each of these four compounds to
determine whether or not they're going
to be aromatic so if we take a look at
this first compound here we see that it
meets the first criteria it does have a
cycle in it the second criteria is that
it has to be planer and if we take a
look all of the carbons that are
participating in this cycle here are SP2
hybridized which would mean they would
be planer remember that this carbon here
even though it's sp3 doesn't impact our
aromaticity because it's not directly
part of this ring the third rule is that
we need to have an odd number of py
cloud electron pairs so here we have 1 2
3 so this one meets all three criteria
so this here would be an aromatic
compound a really stable compound let's
take a look at the second one so it's
got the cycle so good on the first
criteria the second one has to be planer
so we can see that all of the carbons
that are participating in those double
bonds would be SP2 hybridized these ones
here though would not they both have two
hydrogens implied coming off of them so
they would be sp3 hybridized and because
of that this would not be a plain cyclic
compound so this one here would not be
aromatic let's try again on the third
one so here cyclic it is it may look
like a square but that's still a cyclic
compound the second criteria planer all
of these carbons are SP2 hybridized so
we're doing well so far the third
criteria an odd number of py cloud
electrons in this case we actually have
two so this would be a different kind of
compound and it would be called
anti-aromatic so whereas aromatic
compounds are particularly stable
anti-aromatic compounds are particularly
unstable so this would definitely not
fall in the aromatic category and the
fourth and final one here we see cyclic
so we're meeting that criteria the
second one SP2 hybridize so this would
be SP2 SP2 SP2 and SP2 this one here
kind of defies expectation so this would
have a hydrogen coming off and if you
counted you have 1 2 3 four areas of
electron density which is typically
going to be labeled sp3 but now this is
the thing right we have all these rules
to help us understand molecules but they
don't follow our rules and they do
whatever leads to the greatest stability
most often so in this case here if this
one adopted an SP2 hybridization then it
would have one 2 three pie Cloud
electron pairs meaning that would make
it aromatic and that actually is what
this compound does so this one may not
look at initial
but this one would fall under an
aromatic heading so that's pretty much
how you apply the rules to understand
whether or not a compound is
[Music]
aromatic